BRIAN J. ARNOLD

DATA SCIENTIST | COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGIST

CONTACT

651-206-2522 brianjohnarnold@gmail.com <u>brian-arnold.github.io</u>

SKILLS

Software
Statistics
Machine learning
Bioinformatics
Computing
Data Analytics
Communication
Strategic thinking

EDUCATION

Harvard University **2009-2015**

PhD in Biology

University of Minnesota – Twin Cities

2004-2008

BS in Plant Biology

PROFILE

Highly adaptive computational biologist with 9+ years of professional data-science experience, specializing in machine learning, software (Python and R), and analysis of diverse data modalities. Successfully led projects from conception to completion and significantly improved analytical capabilities of research teams by managing large datasets with scalable solutions. Learns fast, works hard, and navigates uncertainty well.

EXPERIENCE

Biomedical Data Scientist, Princeton University **2020-Present**

- Packaged new software to optimize neural networks that segment tissues in spatial transcriptomics data and run at scale.
- Led image segmentation and machine learning analyses of 3D videos to quantify neural activity from animal behavior experiments
- Managed 2 trainees on large scale sequencing projects involving 700+ samples and 10+ TB of data
- Collaborated with 9+ groups, authored papers in Science, Nature Methods (pending), Nature Reviews Microbiology, and Genome Biology

Senior Bioinformatician, Harvard University

2018-2020

- Created and published workflow to massively parallelize mutation detection in whole-genome sequences
- Designed machine learning classifier to detect horizontal gene transfer in whole-genome alignments

Postdoctoral Researcher, Harvard School of Public Health **2015-2018**

 Designed fast, memory-efficient C++ code to simulate models of bacterial evolution and used Bayesian
 Optimization to fit these models to data